Christian Hubicki: Fantastic. So, first off, it's really great to have you all here today. I really appreciate it. This is… this… I got to do a workshop with you all last year, and it was a lot of fun, so I appreciate getting to do it again. And…
Christian Hubicki: So, last year, I gave a talk on, for the MC Summer Institute on optimal control methods and optimal control modeling, which,
Christian Hubicki: which I enjoyed giving, and it's still online if you want to check it out. But one of the things that we kind of took for granted when I did that workshop was that you all know how to simulate the movement
Christian Hubicki: of an organism, an animal, a robot in my case. So we decided to sort of back it off a little bit this year in this… and have our topic be about how you simulate movement from scratch, because
Christian Hubicki: I don't know about you all, I'm not… but I'm not sure when in your education you learn how to write computer simulations of movement. I mean, if you're… I'm an engineer, by the way, hello?
Christian Hubicki: Let me start over here. Hello, I'm Christian Hubicki, I'm an associate professor of mechanical engineering. It doesn't say biology in my title, but I love collaborating on biology projects, and as we all know, there are many ways that biology applies to many different disciplines and movement science.
Christian Hubicki: So, I'm going to talk today about how you simulate movement, because simulation is something you do a lot in my field. So, you know, many of us know all about, have seen a lot of Monica's work. Make sure we get this going here.
Christian Hubicki: Alright…
Christian Hubicki: So, here's an example of a thing that moves. Monica's, I think, I don't know if it's your original research subject, but, you know, probably one of your most famous is the guinea fowl. We've seen many
Christian Hubicki: Videos of these things running around on obstacle courses, very stably, and they move.
Christian Hubicki: Right? And experiment… and experiments are so important for getting data out of animals.
Christian Hubicki: And I was actually put on a project working on this with Monica back when I was a grad student, but my field is less about animals directly and more about, my subject, robots.
Christian Hubicki: I work in robotics, okay? So, where do… where do we connect on this? And a lot of it is in the field of simulation. How do we make a simulation of an animal?
Christian Hubicki: Okay? In a way that's helpful. And why would you want to do that? Okay? …
Christian Hubicki: And, well, in robotics, the reason we want to have simulations is we want to be able to write controllers, and so one thing we will do is we will take a robot, we will write a computer simulation.
Christian Hubicki: and have an algorithm try to optimize how that simulation moves to come up with a controller for a walking robot, and that's what this here is. So, the first thing we had to do before we controlled this robot was how to simulate it, okay?
Christian Hubicki: And so, that's my specialty, and particularly the optimal control thereof.
Christian Hubicki: But, more importantly.
Christian Hubicki: for, I believe, the Summer Institute is that simulations are math models, right? It offers another way to look into and interrogate the motion of organisms. If you have a simulation, you can try all kinds of things. You would never think of trying with an animal, and test all kinds of hypotheses as to why the animal was doing what it's doing without an experiment, or, more importantly, in complement with an experiment.
Christian Hubicki: probably very, you know, right in this paper that Monica had written back in 2006, she used a pretty simplified math model, right here.
Christian Hubicki: What's called a spring-loaded inverted pendulum to model how this guinea fowl steps into an obstacle.
Christian Hubicki: and then falls forward, and yet still maintains its stability, okay? So, simplify, and to do that, Monica had to write a computer simulation.
Christian Hubicki: Of movement, right?
Christian Hubicki: And…
Christian Hubicki: From my standpoint, from a robotic standpoint, math models are also important for how you design robots, as well as control them. If you have some simple bio-inspired model for simulation, something simplified, you can use it to inform how your robots are built, as well as how to control them. And theoretically, if you have a reasonable bio-inspired model.
Christian Hubicki: that guides your control and your design, you could end up with animal-like movement as a consequence. That's a hypothesis we've seen, that we've toyed with a lot in the past.
Christian Hubicki: And Mac models can come in all shapes and sizes, right? This is OpenSim, you know, it's been downloaded hundreds of thousands of times.
Christian Hubicki: Which is… which allows your models to be complex and musculoskeletal.
Christian Hubicki: And probably is what a lot of people might think of when they're thinking of simulation, is these really complicated models. But, they can also be incredibly simple. This is a model, a very simple model of a predator-prey interaction modeled by my student, Jacob Hackett. The idea is that this, like, this little rat is running away from some kind of owl that's chasing it down. And you have a very simplified model, which is just a little mass that's being pushed around by a force.
Christian Hubicki: And they're trying to avoid each other using optimal control, right?
Christian Hubicki: So… You can also use optimal control… you can also use models with optimal control for prediction.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? That if you have a reduced-order model, a very simple simulation model, and you hypothesize what the animal might want, what its objectives are, what its rewards are, right, and you take that model, and you give it to an algorithm that optimizes its motion with control, okay, you can have it make a prediction as to how the animal will move. What we're looking at right here is a sagittal plane trajectory of a stance phase and a
Christian Hubicki: flight phase for a running guinea fowl, or at least a simulated running guinea fowl, and there's your ground reaction forces right there that you would typically see if you measured them in the ground. We can try to make predictions as to how they would move on different terrain, okay? And this is an example from a paper that Monica and I had written together with one of her intrepid graduate students. It was a real humdinger of a paper, lots of stuff involved, but one small piece of it…
Christian Hubicki: Was making an optimal control prediction of how the ground reaction forces
Christian Hubicki: can reflect the energy injection of a stance phase across all these different species of birds, okay?
Christian Hubicki: So…
Christian Hubicki: what I want to impart upon you today are some of the basics of how you would simulate these animals, alright? And…
Christian Hubicki: it can become very complicated, like, if we go back to our, to the OpenSim model, you know, if you're trying to work with a very complex musculoskeletal model, thankfully, they already have packages you can download and some tutorials that you can run.
Christian Hubicki: But one thing we find, at least I found in, of course, throughout my time as a researcher, is having a bespoke, simplified model can be super helpful in a lot of ways for being able to interrogate how an animal would move, and test hypotheses about it.
Christian Hubicki: So, that's what we're gonna do today, is figure out how to take a much simpler model.
Christian Hubicki: And then actually run… write a computer simulation. We're gonna do it in MATLAB today.
Christian Hubicki: From scratch, in case you have never done this before. And I'll cover some of the basics of how we're gonna do this, and so…
Christian Hubicki: So, what we're gonna do today is we're gonna try to simulate, some hopping.
Christian Hubicki: with a spring-loaded inverted pendulum, okay? It's a classic model, alright? And so we're gonna start from scratch, we're gonna make a mass with a spring, maybe a little damper, and have it hop around. This one has a second leg in it, just because… why not? But we can see how far we get today, and as a result, we're gonna cover
Christian Hubicki: How we're gonna do simulation at all.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? All the basics of it. We're gonna get the equations for this model.
Christian Hubicki: And we're gonna simulate them. And we're gonna see how it goes. So, with that.
Christian Hubicki: I'd recommend opening up MATLAB. You don't have to download any code to start, you don't need any toolboxes, just open up MATLAB, and we'll get started, and I'll start drawing out things on my little whiteboard here.
Christian Hubicki: To get us started.
Christian Hubicki: So… If you want to simulate movement, okay, so simulating movement.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: The first thing you're gonna need is a model.
Christian Hubicki: Or what we call in our business, a dynamical.
Christian Hubicki: system.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: And what that means is we have some equation that defines how it moves, how the system moves, given its current position, its state, and any control that you want to add.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? And that sounds pretty abstract, and I'm gonna start talking about a little bit of math, but just to be clear, the kind of math that we're talking about for this talk is, do you know what a derivative is from calculus? Right? That's… that is my…
Christian Hubicki: that's my starting point for how we're talking about math today. I'm sure many of you are experts in simulation, at which point, you know, treat this as a nice vacation of thinking about simple simulations here, but for those who haven't, and I imagine that's a lot of people, that's all you need to know. What is a derivative, okay? So…
Christian Hubicki: And that's important because we define
Christian Hubicki: dynamical systems…
Christian Hubicki: Which are… systems, That vary with time.
Christian Hubicki: Which is a lot of things, like movement, Appropriately enough.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: by the… time derivative.
Christian Hubicki: of key variables.
Christian Hubicki: And those are… those key variables, they have a special name, they're gonna be called state variables, and we'll get to that in a second, right? Basically, you're getting a crash course
Christian Hubicki: And the basics of dynamical systems and how you simulate them, okay?
Christian Hubicki: Or, well, it's a survivor… survival guide. How about that? Alright. So, now recall we have a… so imagine…
Christian Hubicki: And take a typical population model. Example… A population model.
Christian Hubicki: Okay, let's say you have a population model For some population P.
Christian Hubicki: Of rodents in the desert.
Christian Hubicki: Right? And how much do they multiply, right? So you can see that it's varying with respect to T, which is time.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? And so our dynamical… our dynamical system would be defined by the… How much the population changes
Christian Hubicki: DPDT, your time derivative, is gonna be dependent upon your population. It's gonna be dependent upon your population.
Christian Hubicki: times some… Alpha constant right there. Okay.
Christian Hubicki: Road's in the desert, no better system. I agree, Clint.
Christian Hubicki: I agree.
Christian Hubicki: Okay.
Christian Hubicki: Fantastic, right? So, basically, the more rodents you have, the more they're going to multiply. Now, of course, you're going to be limited by environment, so you can add other terms here, but this is a really simple population model, right? So, basically, you're saying, you know, this is how much
Christian Hubicki: Your population changes.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? It's a time… it's a derivative, right? It's derivative with respect to time, right?
Christian Hubicki: And when you have an equation with derivatives in it, does anyone know what that's called in math?
Christian Hubicki: Anybody? I know many of you are being polite and not answering, because you're waiting for the students to answer.
Christian Hubicki: But yeah.
Casey King: forensical location?
Christian Hubicki: Differential equation, Casey, that's right. It's called a differential equation, right?
Christian Hubicki: Hope this isn't overly tutorial for everyone. Hopefully someone is learning something.
Christian Hubicki: It's a differential equation, right? It's that thing that, if you're not a math major or an engineer or something like that, you might not have to take, necessarily, as part of your curriculum. But that's all a differential equation is. It's an equation with a derivative in it, right? And solving differential equations by hand sometimes can be easy, this one we can solve by hand.
Christian Hubicki: sometimes can be hard.
Christian Hubicki: Right? So…
Christian Hubicki: Basically, if we manage to solve this differential equation, it will tell us what the population of the rodents are going to be in the desert for all time.
Christian Hubicki: For all time, right? Awesome, great. This one we can solve just by… if you took a differential equations class, it's just gonna be an exponential, is what it's gonna turn out to be. You need an initial condition, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera. In fact, …
Christian Hubicki: Yeah, so anyway, you have a… this is your population model, right? But there are some systems that you… there are some equations that
Christian Hubicki: are harder to solve by hand, right? You know, in fact, I'll write out the answer here, just for everyone's completion's sake. Oh, the solution…
Christian Hubicki: would be P of T is equal to some constant C times E to the alpha T.
Christian Hubicki: Right? That's the solution. So, we would know it has this exponential curve, and this little constant C right here, that defines the initial condition, that's your starting population, for instance, right?
Christian Hubicki: But guess what?
Christian Hubicki: You don't have to know how to do that for today. You don't need to know how to solve these by hand, right? And there's a good reason for that, is because while this is a simple system, I'll give you another simple system. I will… I will swing it. There's my…
Christian Hubicki: The pendulum. We all know pendulums.
Christian Hubicki: We've probably seen them all the time under gravity. I can write out the equations of motion for a pendulum.
Christian Hubicki: Alright, so… so I can write there are… We can write our equations, 4… Sir, our differential equation.
Christian Hubicki: for a pendulum.
Christian Hubicki: Okay. Under gravity. So I'm gonna draw a pendulum.
Christian Hubicki: There we go, not my best work.
Christian Hubicki: Got a little mass at the end, you got some length, L for your pendulum, you're under gravity.
Christian Hubicki: Okay, pendulum, and this is some angle theta of t. That can change over time. That's how you have your dynamical system. It changes over time, right?
Christian Hubicki: So…
Christian Hubicki: You could write out the equations from this by doing… by just doing a force balance, force-moment balance, using a free value diagram. That would save us a little bit of time today, and say that the…
Christian Hubicki: Second derivative.
Christian Hubicki: a theta of t.
Christian Hubicki: DT.
Christian Hubicki: is equal to minus G over L sine of theta of t.
Christian Hubicki: This would not take too long to, to derive. In fact, we'll have to derive some equations for our spring-loaded inverted pendulum, but I'll save us some time. Here's a differential equation.
Christian Hubicki: That doesn't look too bad, right?
Christian Hubicki: Does anyone know how to solve that by hand, like I did the population model?
Christian Hubicki: The answer should be no one, because it's impossible.
Christian Hubicki: is literally an impossible equation to solve, with elementary functions, sines and cosines, exponentials. We know this fact, we've known this for a very, very long time.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: So, it's all lost.
Christian Hubicki: Can we… do we… so does that mean we hang up our hats? No. Clearly, we know how to simulate a pendulum. You know, we have had physics simulators for a long time. We have video games with dynamical systems like pendulums. We have robots, which are basically a bunch of joints that are connected together. They're pendulums.
Christian Hubicki: So what do we do?
Christian Hubicki: So… So we solve the differential equations.
Christian Hubicki: Approximately.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: That solution for that population growth model, that's an exact solution. That is literally the answer to the math question, right?
Christian Hubicki: If we can't get that, we can at least get close.
Christian Hubicki: Alright?
Christian Hubicki: So, the way that we… and so this is often called, you know, solving numerically.
Christian Hubicki: And you are all… if you're doing any kind of simulation in any… in any field, any domain, if you're playing… if you're playing Zelda, and you're throwing lobbing bombs.
Christian Hubicki: at creatures, if you're, if you're, you know, you're, if you're, simulating an animal in OpenSim, or something like that.
Christian Hubicki: They are approximately solving differential equations.
Christian Hubicki: That's all simulation is. Let's put this in red.
Christian Hubicki: Simulation…
Christian Hubicki: of dynamical systems.
Christian Hubicki: is just… solving… differential equations.
Christian Hubicki: That's it.
Christian Hubicki: Okay, that's it.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? So anytime you see a simulation, that's what they're doing of a dynamical system, right?
Christian Hubicki: So… So what do we do? Okay?
Christian Hubicki: So… So how?
Christian Hubicki: Alright? And we'll cover one of the simplest ways, which is to take the definition of a derivative, let's take a definition of a derivative.
Christian Hubicki: D… some variable X of t dt, right?
Christian Hubicki: And what is that? Okay, well, if you remember calculus, The derivative… It's a limit as some… Small…
Christian Hubicki: Delta X, Goes to zero.
Christian Hubicki: Sorry, … sorry, Delta T, I apologize. Delta T.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: of the quantity X of t, plus delta T, minus… X of t.
Christian Hubicki: all over delta T. I jumped straight to the math, I shouldn't have done that, right? What I should do is I should say, hey, let's say I have some graph of time
Christian Hubicki: and this variable over time, right? And whoa! There it is. That's what the graph looks like, right?
Christian Hubicki: If I want to know what the derivative is at that point.
Christian Hubicki: In effect, what you need is the tangent…
Christian Hubicki: At that point, and then you want to know what the slope is.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: And the way that you get that is by saying, hey.
Christian Hubicki: I'm at this time T here.
Christian Hubicki: Now I'm over at some tiny, tiny different spot over here, T plus delta T.
Christian Hubicki: I say, hey, what's the slope between those two points?
Christian Hubicki: That's what a derivative is. What is a derivative?
Christian Hubicki: And the formal definition is when T, delta T here, goes to zero, in the limit. That's what we learn in calculus, right?
Christian Hubicki: But what if it wasn't literally going to zero, but instead was super, super small, okay?
Christian Hubicki: What if… Delta T, is… Really small.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Then we would say the same equation over again, where we would say, okay, well, dx dt…
Christian Hubicki: of T is approximately equal to…
Christian Hubicki: X of t plus delta T minus X of t, all over delta T.
Christian Hubicki: So, instead of the limit as it going to zero, you just say, hey, just, you know, delta T is small.
Christian Hubicki: It's small, and this is almost right.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: Which is cool, because what that means is, I can then say, hey, In the future.
Christian Hubicki: This is… I want to know what this… I want to know what X is in the future. That's what solving a differential equation is. I want to know what's happening in the future, right?
Christian Hubicki: I can just solve for this using good old algebra.
Christian Hubicki: Multiply both sides by delta T.
Christian Hubicki: then add X of t to the other side. I can just solve that really quick.
Christian Hubicki: And I would say, well, X of t plus delta T It's approximately equal to… X of t, Plus.
Christian Hubicki: DX of T, DT?
Christian Hubicki: Times delta.
Christian Hubicki: iPad's misbehaving.
Christian Hubicki: times delta T.
Christian Hubicki: Alright?
Christian Hubicki: Hopefully people can follow that algebra well enough. We just put this on the other side, and then added this to the other side, boop, and then rearranged them back and forth, that's it.
Christian Hubicki: So now we know approximately what the future will look like, based upon where we are now at the current time t.
Christian Hubicki: plus the… Rate of change, the time derivative, times delta T.
Christian Hubicki: This is super common.
Christian Hubicki: Methods called Euler's method.
Christian Hubicki: Okay.
Christian Hubicki: And it's near and dear to my heart, because one, it's super easy, we just derived it, it's done. Also, my postdoc advisor's advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, advisors, was Leonard Euler. So…
Christian Hubicki: Probably like a lot of people in this collaboration, to be honest, but… you know.
Christian Hubicki: Gotta do well by great-grandpa.
Christian Hubicki: Okay.
Christian Hubicki: Anyway, this is the simplest way, this little equation here.
Christian Hubicki: is the simplest way that we can approximately solve a differential equation. And what does it mean? It means that we have some tiny time step t.
Christian Hubicki: And we say, hey, where do we start?
Christian Hubicki: We add this term, we say, hey, how much are we changing, multiply it by how long we're changing for, and then we get the next time step.
Christian Hubicki: And then we repeat over and over and over and over and over and over again until we've simulated for so much, so many little time steps that they add up to a long period of time.
Christian Hubicki: So, let's go back to our population example.
Christian Hubicki: where we said we had some DP of T,
Christian Hubicki: DT, some change in population over time, is equal to some constant alpha times whatever your population is.
Christian Hubicki: And we say, here's time, here's our population.
Christian Hubicki: Here's time zero.
Christian Hubicki: And we have to tell us… we have to tell us, to ourselves, what is… the starting population.
Christian Hubicki: And more generally, we call it the initial condition.
Christian Hubicki: Because that matters, right?
Christian Hubicki: Now, I'm no ratologist, but I imagine when there are zero rats, they proliferate at a different rate when there are two rats.
Christian Hubicki: Right? To start with.
Christian Hubicki: That's just my lay understanding of the matter.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? So…
Christian Hubicki: So let's say we start off with some number of rats, then we know… confirmed, okay, Clint confirms this scientific fact. Thank you, Clint.
Christian Hubicki: Good.
Christian Hubicki: Alright? So we are currently… At this time here.
Christian Hubicki: Right? This is now.
Christian Hubicki: Welcome to NOW.
Christian Hubicki: Alright.
Christian Hubicki: And the amount of time… so now I'm going to use Euler's method.
Christian Hubicki: And by the way, the cool kids call it Euler's method, my granddaddy would like it that way, not Euler's.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? I asked him.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Alright? We're gonna say, hey, the next time…
Christian Hubicki: of P plus some delta T is gonna equal the sum P of T, the current population.
Christian Hubicki: Plus, the change in population, At the rate of change of population times… This tiny delta T, right?
Christian Hubicki: So…
Christian Hubicki: Let's find out!
Christian Hubicki: After one small time step, what are populations gonna be?
Christian Hubicki: Well, we know what our population is now, we said it's that, alright? And now we say, okay, well, what's the change over time? Well, we have this equation up here.
Christian Hubicki: It's this alpha P of T, right?
Christian Hubicki: Let's assume alpha's positive. This is a positive rate of growth. These are…
Christian Hubicki: proliferating rats, okay? That means that this is going to be some positive number proportional to the current population.
Christian Hubicki: and you multiply it by some delta T. So, this is all going to be some positive number.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: So, after some tiny period of time, delta T, that means it's gonna go boop!
Christian Hubicki: Like that, up a little bit, right?
Christian Hubicki: Now we're gonna step… now this is now, right?
Christian Hubicki: That's now.
Christian Hubicki: Okay, and now we're going to move forward again in time, because we want to know what happens over time.
Christian Hubicki: And now our population is… Bigger.
Christian Hubicki: It's bigger there than it was here.
Christian Hubicki: So when we're doing this calculation again, we're moving forward in time again.
Christian Hubicki: We now take our current population, which is this.
Christian Hubicki: And now we add this term, which is now more, because our population is now bigger, right?
Christian Hubicki: So…
Christian Hubicki: So it goes up at a greater rate of change, right?
Christian Hubicki: And guess what? It keeps doing this.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: And that's going to approximate, you know, that's going to end up looking like the answer that we all know
Christian Hubicki: And people who took differential equations, or know how to solve them, it's gonna look like E to the C, e to the AT. It looks like that. It's an exponential growth, right?
Christian Hubicki: Multiplying like rabbits, or rats in this case, right?
Christian Hubicki: That's what it looks like. So, we didn't have to know
Christian Hubicki: all the cool tricks from the differential equations class, how to solve that equation. It's okay, we got this approximated version of it, right?
Christian Hubicki: it just takes a lot more, sort of, churning and churning of the numbers, right? We have to do this equation over and over and over again, right?
Christian Hubicki: So… That's it.
Christian Hubicki: In fact, why don't we code up the multiplying… you know what? This'll be quick. Let's code up in MATLAB,
Christian Hubicki: The rat.
Christian Hubicki: population model. Well, we'll show you how simple it can be, alright?
Christian Hubicki: So I want to go back over to…
Christian Hubicki: ye olde MATLAB… actually, let me go back here.
Christian Hubicki: I'm raising my…
Christian Hubicki: Alright, and… there we go.
Christian Hubicki: So, let's make a… I have MATLAB open here.
Christian Hubicki: And I just got a very simple script open, I just opened up a new file, alright?
Christian Hubicki: I'm going to… we're gonna create a new file, we're gonna call it… Population…
Christian Hubicki: sim.m. Can you read that? I can make the text bigger if it would be helpful to read it.
Christian Hubicki: How about that?
Monica Daley (she, her): A little bigger might help, yeah.
Christian Hubicki: Okay, let's do that.
Christian Hubicki: Alright.
Christian Hubicki: I'm also recording this in 4K on my own computer, Victoria, if you want to upload that instead. So….
Victoria Wood: That'll be great, thanks.
Christian Hubicki: So I'm gonna… you got it.
Christian Hubicki: So, but hopefully people read it now. So I'm gonna create… I'm gonna save this file, I'm gonna call it PopulationSim.
Christian Hubicki: dot M, okay?
Christian Hubicki: Alright? Written by… myself, And friends, that's what the original etol Latin stands for, okay?
Christian Hubicki: Alright, we're written and writing this together. Alright, so today…
Christian Hubicki: 20… the 21st of August of the Common Era, so there's no confusion. Alright? So we're just gonna simulate…
Christian Hubicki: the population, Growth.
Christian Hubicki: of… Rats.
Christian Hubicki: Without resource limitations.
Christian Hubicki: Right? Nothing is… Or predation, I guess.
Christian Hubicki: Anyway, simple model, right? So, for those that's been a while to do MATLAB, to do any MATLABing here, the first thing I like to do when I create a new MATLAB script is I clear everything.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: And I clear everything. The way I do this, I say, CLC, CLC, all it does is…
Christian Hubicki: Clear the screen. It clears the main screen, if there's anything down there.
Christian Hubicki: Clear, clears all the variables.
Christian Hubicki: And close all closes all the plots. Alright? And clear everything.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? Alright.
Christian Hubicki: So now I need… so now I need to define my simulation parameters. Let me actually pull up the, …
Christian Hubicki: Math again. So what are we gonna need to know? Oh, actually, I'll just put this over here.
Christian Hubicki: So, what are we gonna need to know? We need to know…
Christian Hubicki: We need to define what our delta T
Christian Hubicki: is. We have to define what our alpha is.
Christian Hubicki: And we have to define our population at time zero, that's our initial pop, right?
Christian Hubicki: Okay? And we also want to know what the final time is. How long do we want to simulate this for? How long do we want to know… to simulate this for? Those are the four things that we're going to need to define, okay? So let's define those parameters here. Actually, let's move this aside so we can see it.
Christian Hubicki: In spite of everything here.
Christian Hubicki: So we got, … so, define our parameters.
Christian Hubicki: Alright, so we're gonna get our… call it our delta T.
Christian Hubicki: We'll make it 0.01, okay? Alright, it's a small… it needs to be small. Now, how small?
Christian Hubicki: Good question. …
Christian Hubicki: So glad we didn't use Clear Hall, bad habits still lingering from your student days. Oh, thanks, Jordan. That's good to know. Yeah, I just use Clear these days.
Christian Hubicki: Alright, so DT, let's get our T final, let's simulate for 10 units of time. Now, I was a bad boy, I did not define my units in this model, but you'll… we're gonna move, we're gonna press forward to get this out the door so we can keep moving forward. …
Christian Hubicki: So, this is gonna be our final time.
Christian Hubicki: Alright? We're gonna need our alpha, which is some parameter. I'm just gonna call it 0.5, some… this is some rate of population growth.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? And we've got… our initial population, we'll call it P0.
Christian Hubicki: We'll start with… Two animals, alright?
Christian Hubicki: initial population.
Christian Hubicki: Okay, so what we're gonna do is, in order to do this simulation where we are constantly, you know, reapplying Euler's method over and over again, what are we gonna need in encoding structures? We're gonna need a loop, right? So what we're gonna need is a simulation…
Christian Hubicki: loop, okay?
Christian Hubicki: I'm gonna go a little non-linearly in terms of the code and motivate some things later, but what we're gonna wanna do is…
Christian Hubicki: Is start at our first time, which is time 0.
Christian Hubicki: Compute what the next population is, and then the next, and the next, and the next, and the next, and we want to store it all
Christian Hubicki: in a big vector, in a big array, okay? In MATLAB, we call arrays vectors for the most part. And it's just good practice to say, hey, let's define
Christian Hubicki: all of the size of all of our vectors beforehand, and not just make them bigger, bigger, bigger, bigger, bigger, bigger, bigger as the loop goes along. This is called pre-allocation, okay?
Christian Hubicki: It just… it helps speed up your simulation, and it's better for memory usage. It's just good practice to do it. Pre-allocation of arrays.
Christian Hubicki: So what we're gonna need is…
Christian Hubicki: And we're gonna, we're gonna store our time.
Christian Hubicki: In an array?
Christian Hubicki: And the way that we can store it is we can say we want it to start at time 0,
Christian Hubicki: Go in increments of DT,
Christian Hubicki: And end at T final. That's the MATLAB syntax for it, with colons, and that will count up, right?
Christian Hubicki: Alright? And… they're gonna call it… they're gonna create a population array.
Christian Hubicki: Now, we do not know what the population is going to be at all these different time points, but… so for now, we'll just call them zero and change them later. So, in MATLAB, we would say, hey, zeros.
Christian Hubicki: And we want it to be the same size as the time array, because for every time… point in time, we want a population. The way you can say this is say, hey, what's the size of our time array?
Christian Hubicki: And Ocrate Zero is of the exact same size.
Christian Hubicki: That's it.
Christian Hubicki: what I can do is I can run the code to make sure I don't have any errors, no errors yet.
Christian Hubicki: Okay.
Christian Hubicki: Alright, so now we have our… Populu… time array, population array.
Christian Hubicki: Then we need to set our initial condition.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? Which means that the first element of our population array
Christian Hubicki: I'm using tab to help complete, in case you're not familiar with the syntax.
Christian Hubicki: So, the very first element, and in MATLAB, we would say, open parentheses 1, closed parentheses. The very first element, the very first number in that list, let's change it to our starting population, which is P0.
Christian Hubicki: Great.
Christian Hubicki: Cool.
Christian Hubicki: Now we need to do a simulation loop. Now, if you're doing a loop with a known number of steps in the loop, we use what's called a for loop. I'm sure many of you are super familiar. So you say 4, and you have some iteration variable, I call it iter.
Christian Hubicki: In MATLAB, I don't like to call it I, because I is already taken as the imaginary number. I don't use M, because M is almost always mass in my simulations, and I have made my mass increase over time by mistake in my simulations by calling it M. Yes, yeah, I'm glad you… I'm glad you appreciate Victoria.
Christian Hubicki: The, so, alright. So, and you're going to go through one colon, the number of elements, it's N-U-M-E-L, that's the number of elements in your time vector, in your time array. So, time array.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: And one little thing that might not be obvious is that you're gonna have to subtract one. So this is… so if we… and the reason is, is that we're gonna have to start with the second time step, because we know what the answer to the first time step is, it's the initial condition. So if we're going to start at the second one, we're not going to count through every element, just all elements minus 1, okay?
Christian Hubicki: So, this is gonna count through all the elements.
Christian Hubicki: And then we say, population array
Christian Hubicki: iter plus 1, we're indexing in by saying the next one, right, is equal to…
Christian Hubicki: I put a little dot dot dot ellipses, just because my text is so giant.
Christian Hubicki: So we can go on to the next line. Okay, is equal to the… what's… let's pull up the…
Christian Hubicki: Man, let's pull up our… Willer's method right here, right?
Christian Hubicki: So this basically is saying that your next Time step.
Christian Hubicki: Care?
Christian Hubicki: is equal to your previous time, plus the change times delta T.
Christian Hubicki: So… The population, So it means the population array, which is the current population, which is the current iteration.
Christian Hubicki: Plus… Now we are into the DPDT right here.
Christian Hubicki: And what is that? Well, that's this equation up here. It's just alpha times the current population.
Christian Hubicki: So, plus… Alpha?
Christian Hubicki: Times the current population, which is, again, population array, iter?
Christian Hubicki: times… Delta T.
Christian Hubicki: DT.
Christian Hubicki: Semicolon.
Christian Hubicki: And the loop!
Christian Hubicki: That's it.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Now we're going to plot the results.
Christian Hubicki: I'm gonna use the plot command, I'm gonna plot our time array on the horizontal axis, and the population array.
Christian Hubicki: On the vertical axis, I'm gonna make a nice black line.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: And just because it'd be hard to see on your… over Zoom, I'm going to add another parameter here. You could say, hey, I want the line width.
Christian Hubicki: here to be, I don't know, 3? That's pretty thick.
Christian Hubicki: Alright, I'll let you all take a look at that here.
Christian Hubicki: This will make the… this will allow you to plot the results.
Christian Hubicki: I'm going to be a good boy and label my axes.
Christian Hubicki: Good scientist. This is time in some units that I have not defined.
Christian Hubicki: And Y label?
Christian Hubicki: Give me my population.
Christian Hubicki: Once I have that.
Christian Hubicki: Hopefully it actually runs.
Christian Hubicki: The new installation of MATLAB is gonna have all kinds of interesting… There we go.
Christian Hubicki: Get that out of your way so you can see a little better of the code. If anyone needs to see any, I'll make this smaller so you can all see, but hopefully you can see
Christian Hubicki: the exponential… Curve increase right there, right? Perfect. Exactly as we predicted. Nifty, great, awesome, cool.
Christian Hubicki: Alright? But that is not a spring-loaded inverted pendulum.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? So how do we get there in 45 minutes?
Christian Hubicki: Trust me.
Christian Hubicki: That's how we do it. Okay. Alright. So…
Christian Hubicki: Here's the thing, so hopefully, any questions about this so far? Hopefully, I tried to keep it reasonably basic here, but happy to backtrack here.
Christian Hubicki: … So… Let's go back to… in the meantime…
Christian Hubicki: So now let's go to some… a system that's a little bit more complicated, right? Okay. So first, a couple things that you're gonna notice. So, notice…
Christian Hubicki: that the Euler's method
Christian Hubicki: has a few properties, okay, that we want to notice here, okay? One, so…
Christian Hubicki: We look X of t plus delta T.
Christian Hubicki: is equal to… equal to X of T… plus… DX of T…
Christian Hubicki: DT times delta T, right? We have that Euler's method.
Christian Hubicki: Alright, a few things we want to notice.
Christian Hubicki: Number one, It is derived using an equation where there's only one derivative.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? And…
Christian Hubicki: Many equations, including our pendulum, have multiple derivatives, okay? So, what we would call that is, we'd call that a first order.
Christian Hubicki: differential equation.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: First order means only one derivative.
Christian Hubicki: So that's… it applied to… it worked really well for this population model, but how's it going to work with things with multiple derivatives? So, I'll scroll back up to my pendulum…
Christian Hubicki: Right here.
Christian Hubicki: That's a second derivative right there, with respect to theta, right? So how are we gonna have to learn how to deal with that?
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Number 2…
Christian Hubicki: It's exhausting to write DX of t, dt, or d theta of t, dt over and over again. So…
Christian Hubicki: Those of us who work in dynamical systems have a very simple way of writing it.
Christian Hubicki: We say that DX sub T dt, We write it as… X dot.
Christian Hubicki: of tea.
Christian Hubicki: Saves us carpal tunnel.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? That's a common notation, that for every time derivative, you put a dot.
Christian Hubicki: So, for that equation up above, we would have written theta Double dot.
Christian Hubicki: of tea.
Christian Hubicki: Alright? It's cool.
Christian Hubicki: So, naturally, you're gonna think of.
Christian Hubicki: If it's a position variable that you're taking derivative of, a first derivative is going to be your velocity.
Christian Hubicki: Your second derivative is going to be your
Christian Hubicki: Acceleration. I'm gonna start asking for more derivatives for people ready to unmute themselves. Anyone know what the third derivative is typically called of position?
Christian Hubicki: There's multiple names.
Christian Hubicki: But…
Christian Hubicki: This is a fun factoid, called, … Yeah, thanks, Jordan.
Christian Hubicki: X triple dot?
Christian Hubicki: If it's position, That's called jerk.
Christian Hubicki: Some people call it jounce.
Christian Hubicki: Yeah, not calling me names, Jordan, I appreciate that.
Christian Hubicki: Thank you, thank you. Anyone know what, … X quadrupledine is?
Monica Daley (she, her): Snap.
Christian Hubicki: Yeah, snap, thank you.
Christian Hubicki: X12345… Crackle.
Christian Hubicki: And X123456…
Christian Hubicki: is… pop, and I'm not making that up. I actually tried to find the oldest… yeah, Snap, Crackle Pop… tried to find the… find who decided this.
Christian Hubicki: Who made this name? I managed to trace it back to at least Usenet forums in the early 90s.
Christian Hubicki: People were talking about what they should call them. …
Christian Hubicki: that's as far back as I've gone, as to who decide… what businesses decided to call them Snack Crackle Pop. Anyway, we won't go, probably, that far to Jerk, Snack Crackle Pop.
Christian Hubicki: But anyway, fun little aside.
Christian Hubicki: Alright? But the point is, we're gonna have to deal with higher order derivatives, alright? Okay.
Christian Hubicki: Another thing that you need to… that you'll notice is that there's only a derivative with respect to time.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: That there's no derivative with respect to space, there's no derivative with respect to any other variable, right?
Christian Hubicki: And that means it's going to be what we call an ordinary.
Christian Hubicki: First, ordinary differential equation. Sorry, I can't read that.
Christian Hubicki: ordinary differential equation, okay? So… We're dealing with ordinary, for ordinary… Differential equations, Diffie Q's, Otherwise called ODEs.
Christian Hubicki: And we are dealing with first order.
Christian Hubicki: ODEs.
Christian Hubicki: So, how do we make Euler's method work?
Christian Hubicki: when it only works for first-order ODEs, there are ways to make it work other ways, but here's a way, okay?
Christian Hubicki: The trick is that if you have any higher order ODE,
Christian Hubicki: with more derivatives, there's always a way to turn it into multiple first-order derivatives, differential equations. There's always a way.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? And it's a pretty simple formula to do it, alright? …
Christian Hubicki: So let's, let's go, let's go talk about…
Christian Hubicki: Let's start motivating our spring-loaded inverted pendulum, and we'll show you how, from this example.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? You have spring-loaded inverted pendulum, otherwise known as the slip model.
Christian Hubicki: Always an interesting term, because it does not slip.
Christian Hubicki: By definition. Its foot sticks on the ground and it does not move.
Christian Hubicki: But, it's called the slip.
Christian Hubicki: Alright? And we're just gonna start with a 1D version, meaning it's just going to hop up and down. So we've got a mass…
Christian Hubicki: We got a spring, and we're just gonna start on the ground. We're not even gonna leave the ground yet. So, we're just gonna have some vertical position.
Christian Hubicki: call it Z of T.
Christian Hubicki: In legged locomotion, a lot of times, up is Z, because Y is that way and X is that way, right? Okay.
Christian Hubicki: So…
Christian Hubicki: Alright, so we… so what we can get the equations of motion for our dynamical system, and it's gonna basically be our F equals MA,
Christian Hubicki: Force equal to mass times acceleration, where in our case, our acceleration is going to be Z double dot of T.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? And we're gonna sum all of our forces, and the only forces we're gonna have are gonna be gravity.
Christian Hubicki: and this spring force, okay? And we're gonna have some…
Christian Hubicki: Rest length of this spring, zero. You need a rest length for your spring, okay?
Christian Hubicki: So we're going to… so here we're going to derive the equations of motions ourselves, it's not very hard. There are toolboxes, symbolic toolboxes, that'll do this for you, if you have a complicated system. Okay, but here, let's just to make it for transparency, we're just going to derive it really quickly.
Christian Hubicki: And so we're gonna sum all the forces of the free-by diagram.
Christian Hubicki: Down, we've got MG for gravity.
Christian Hubicki: And pushing up, we have some spring constant K times the deflection of the spring.
Christian Hubicki: and it's gonna be L0 minus
Christian Hubicki: the, the, the height Z of T, okay?
Christian Hubicki: So, that means when the rest length is longer than the actual length, that means it's going to want to push it up, and up is the positive direction for Z. So, when L0 is longer than Z of T, positive. Okay? So, we sum all of our forces.
Christian Hubicki: So is equal to the mass times the acceleration, Z dot double dot of T.
Christian Hubicki: is equal to minus MG plus K L0… minus Z of T.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: There's our equation of motion right there. Boom, boom, boom, boom.
Christian Hubicki: That's the side.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: So how do we simulate that using Euler's method?
Christian Hubicki: Because you can see, we have a second derivative.
Christian Hubicki: Right? So we gotta turn this into… Good.
Christian Hubicki: convert this…
Christian Hubicki: to a system, of… First order.
Christian Hubicki: ODEs.
Christian Hubicki: How do we do that?
Christian Hubicki: Well, what we do is we say, hey, you know what?
Christian Hubicki: Instead of just caring about one variable.
Christian Hubicki: that we're taking two derivatives of, let's create
Christian Hubicki: Two variables that we take one derivative of.
Christian Hubicki: Then we have two first-order differential equations.
Christian Hubicki: So we would say, hey, let's create So we create… A set of variables.
Christian Hubicki: that represents… The higher order system.
Christian Hubicki: Using… Only.
Christian Hubicki: First order… ODEs.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: So, rule of thumb, If it's a second-order system.
Christian Hubicki: You need two of these variables, and they are called… state.
Christian Hubicki: variables.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: And for mechanical systems, which are typically second order because of F equals MA,
Christian Hubicki: Or, there are multiple second-order systems, right?
Christian Hubicki: you will need a… you say, hey, I'm gonna have state variables, we'll call them… Y.
Christian Hubicki: And it's a list of them, a vector of them, and they'll say, hey, it's gonna be…
Christian Hubicki: Z , which is the position.
Christian Hubicki: And Z dot of T, which we all know is the velocity.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: These are our state variables. We put them in a list. Those of you who have seen… ever seen that before, that's a vector, okay? So, and so we often call that the state vector.
Christian Hubicki: And because it's a vector, you know, you've all taken calculus, you all know a vector is a thing that points in a direction. And people are like, oh, mathematicians are like, hey, it's a vector that points in a direction?
Christian Hubicki: That means that any position and velocity together means a different vector and points to a different point in space. So let's call it a space. Let's call it state space, and so you'll see these called state space models.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Right? But, to understand from a survivalist's perspective.
Christian Hubicki: It's just a way of turning your higher order differential equation into multiple.
Christian Hubicki: It's first-order differential equations, and once you have these variables.
Christian Hubicki: You can now say, oh, my… I have this position, I have this velocity, that's all I need to know.
Christian Hubicki: To simulate my system.
Christian Hubicki: So…
Christian Hubicki: Another way to look at this is that the… is that… is that a… is that the state vector here, this list.
Christian Hubicki: Needs to contain all the variables you need, and no more.
Christian Hubicki: to simulate the system. For instance, if I am…
Christian Hubicki: going to simulate the trajectory of this marker, right? If I want to know where… It goes over time.
Christian Hubicki: I need to know where it started.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: And if I don't know the speed at which it starts.
Christian Hubicki: I don't know where it's gonna end up either. So those are the two things I need to know for the position of this marker back and forth, okay? So that's another way to think of the state vector.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? So… How do we use the state vector? Well…
Christian Hubicki: What we can do is we can say, hey, this state vector, let's take the time derivative of it, you know, and it all, you know, it changes over time.
Christian Hubicki: And…
Christian Hubicki: That means that we take the time derivative of everything inside the state vector, so Z of t becomes z dot of t.
Christian Hubicki: and Z dot of T becomes…
Christian Hubicki: Z double dot of T. Make sense? We just took the time derivative of this, which gave us that.
Christian Hubicki: Which means we take the time root of this, which gave us that, and then this, which gave us that, right? That's it, right?
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Then we can rewrite this in terms of things that we know.
Christian Hubicki: what are the things that we know about our system? We would know… we'd have to know where it starts in position, and where it starts in velocity.
Christian Hubicki: So, we know… What the position… what the velocity is.
Christian Hubicki: So we just say that Z dot of T is equal to Z dot of T.
Christian Hubicki: So… We… well, here's a good place. We know this.
Christian Hubicki: We have to know this to simulate.
Christian Hubicki: Good. So at any given point in time, the time derivative of position is velocity, which we know!
Christian Hubicki: Okay.
Christian Hubicki: Now, how about this?
Christian Hubicki: Z double out of T, our acceleration.
Christian Hubicki: That is not one of our state variables, we do not know it as a stored variable.
Christian Hubicki: But can we get it from somewhere?
Christian Hubicki: We absolutely can.
Christian Hubicki: Oop, oop!
Christian Hubicki: There it is.
Christian Hubicki: Right there.
Christian Hubicki: As written in terms of This.
Christian Hubicki: Which is stuff we know.
Christian Hubicki: So we can just take this equation, solve it for Z of T, Z double dot of T,
Christian Hubicki: And we have written…
Christian Hubicki: And I'm just gonna solve it just in my head, so I'm sure I'll make zero mistakes.
Christian Hubicki: I'm gonna solve it by dividing both sides by M, plus K over ML0, sorry, plus K over M…
Christian Hubicki: L0 minus Z… of T.
Christian Hubicki: That's it.
Christian Hubicki: Now, this notation may or may not look familiar to you.
Christian Hubicki: But really, all it's saying is that, hey, we can define The time derivative… of position.
Christian Hubicki: As being equal to the velocity.
Christian Hubicki: Z of T That's one equation.
Christian Hubicki: And, for our second equation, Z double dot of T,
Christian Hubicki: The time derivative of velocity is equal to minus G plus K over M, L0 minus Z of T.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: That's it. Those are two first-order differential equations.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? So that means we can use Euler's method.
Christian Hubicki: We just have to do it twice in a loop.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? Every loop, we do two Euler integrate… we do two Euler approximations, right? We would say… in fact, if it helps, you could call, …
Christian Hubicki: You could call it position… okay, you know, anyway, so…
Christian Hubicki: I'll show you what I mean. Let's make a… we can actually probably do not pass go, go directly…
Christian Hubicki: to… Simulation.
Christian Hubicki: So let's pull up MATLAB.
Christian Hubicki: So, we're now going to do just a 1D pendulum, 1D spring-loaded inverted pendulum, 1D slip, slip 1D. So let's make a new file.
Christian Hubicki: Completely new file.
Christian Hubicki: I'm gonna call it slip1D.m. Gonna save it.
Christian Hubicki: dot M, again, written by me, and all my friends.
Christian Hubicki: That's you.
Christian Hubicki: 2025, 08-21 of the Common Era.
Christian Hubicki: This is gonna be a simulation.
Christian Hubicki: Of a one-dimensional, swing-loaded inverted pendulum, and it's not gonna leave the ground.
Christian Hubicki: So it's gonna stay on the ground, stays on the ground.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? We'll talk about how to get it off the ground in a minute.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Alright.
Christian Hubicki: So… Now we're gonna… what's the first thing I like to do in MATLAB? Clear everything.
Christian Hubicki: This clears the screw… this clears the screen, this clears all the variables, and this closes all the plots, okay?
Christian Hubicki: And now, we need to define our parameters.
Christian Hubicki: I'm gonna do our simulation parameters first.
Christian Hubicki: Then I'm going to do the parameters of the physical model.
Christian Hubicki: So, we have to define, delta T, just like we did before. Let's say .01. Small… Delta small.
Christian Hubicki: time step, it's often called a time step. And if you ever look in the literature, you'll often see this written as the letter H.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? See, that's the letter H, if you're looking in the literature. Okay? You have your time final. Let's simulate this for 10 seconds.
Christian Hubicki: Okay, that's the final time.
Christian Hubicki: We'll do all these in seconds.
Christian Hubicki: Now I understand what the units are, because I… I don't know rodent units of time.
Christian Hubicki: Alright, time there. That's the simulation parameters.
Christian Hubicki: We are now going to… Get our physical model parameters.
Christian Hubicki: And what are our physical model parameters? So let's look at our model here.
Christian Hubicki: I see G as gravity.
Christian Hubicki: So, let's do 9.8.
Christian Hubicki: Meters per second squared, I'm going to make my initial length be 1 meter.
Christian Hubicki: Just make my life easy?
Christian Hubicki: And… your spring constant K?
Christian Hubicki: I think it's powder.
Christian Hubicki: I'm feeling 30. Are you feeling 30? I'm feeling 30 Newtons per meter.
Christian Hubicki: I'm feeling 30.
Christian Hubicki: I reserve the right to change my mind. It's my prerogative.
Christian Hubicki: Okay. Alright. Got physical model parameters, that's great. Now we need our initial conditions.
Christian Hubicki: Right? And we need to know the initial conditions of every state variable.
Christian Hubicki: Of which there are two.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Right there. For our position and our velocity, right?
Christian Hubicki: So let's call it Z0 is the initial position. We'll start at the…
Christian Hubicki: Let's start it right at rest, like 1 meter at rest, so… so 1 meter, okay? And… let's also start it with an initial velocity at zero, which kind of just release it at zero velocity, you know. So DZ0, we'll call it, so this is our initial height.
Christian Hubicki: in meters, This is gonna be our initial… Velocity…
Christian Hubicki: In meters per second, just gonna start it on the ground, just release it, see what it does. Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Now, we start to talk about pre-allocating.
Christian Hubicki: are vectors, right?
Christian Hubicki: So, we… let's call it our time array.
Christian Hubicki: Let's do the same thing as before, we start at time 0,
Christian Hubicki: And… we're gonna go in increments of DT, and it counts up in increments of DT, all the way up to T final.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: We're also gonna do a position array, we'll call it a Z array.
Christian Hubicki: is gonna be the same… is gonna be… we'll start off with some zeros of the same size as our time array, okay? This just creates a bunch of zeros, the same size as the time array.
Christian Hubicki: And then I'm just copying it, I'm being really whimsical and fast, and so I just DZ array. And if you're curious how I'm whippy-dooing around the screen, everyone has their own tricks. What I do is I use Shift, and I hit home.
Christian Hubicki: and I hit END to go back to the right, and, you know, that's what I do. So I'm just using Home and Shift and END to go around, in case you're curious. Everyone has their own approaches. Okay, so we pre-allocated vectors, now that we need to do the simulation loop.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? This is gonna be the Euler simulation loop, and so we'll use another for loop, and we'll do the same thing as before. We'll count up this iterating variable I like to call iter.
Christian Hubicki: from 1 to the number of elements, NUMEL,
Christian Hubicki: And number of elements in our time array.
Christian Hubicki: And again, we're gonna subtract 1, because we already know what the first one is. In fact, I forgot to define what the first one is. So we're gonna say Z array, the very first value.
Christian Hubicki: It's gonna be equal to… Z0.
Christian Hubicki: And I'm gonna say the very first velocity, DZ array, first one, is gonna be equal to DZ0.
Christian Hubicki: Done, right?
Christian Hubicki: Yep, simulation loop.
Christian Hubicki: Alright, so we have for iter, 1 colon, numlarray. Great, now we need to do our Euler's method.
Christian Hubicki: Approximation.
Christian Hubicki: Alright?
Christian Hubicki: So, we can say, according to our math here, that the
Christian Hubicki: This means that of our state variables, we would say that
Christian Hubicki: Z… of T… plus our delta T,
Christian Hubicki: is equal to our current Z of T, Plus…
Christian Hubicki: Our time derivative, which is gonna be…
Christian Hubicki: Z of T at the current time, Times?
Christian Hubicki: Delta T. We can see that well enough. We'll make it a little bit bigger. Boom.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: So… that means we would say that the next element of the Z array, Z array iter plus 1, the next one, is equal to Z array, the current one, which is iter.
Christian Hubicki: Plus… dot dot dot…
Christian Hubicki: Z of T at the current time, which, guess what? We know what that is.
Christian Hubicki: It's DZ array at the current time.
Christian Hubicki: So we'd say… DZ array, that's our velocity.
Christian Hubicki: At the current time, which is iter, times delta T.
Christian Hubicki: That's it.
Christian Hubicki: Those terms right there.
Christian Hubicki: Now we just gotta do the same thing, again, for the DZ array.
Christian Hubicki: Alright? Where?
Christian Hubicki: Z dot… T plus delta T.
Christian Hubicki: Is equal to the current Z dot… I'll make this a little bigger here.
Christian Hubicki: As you can see. Current Z dot… of T.
Christian Hubicki: plus the time derivative of that, which is Z double dot of T times delta T.
Christian Hubicki: That's Euler's method, you know.
Christian Hubicki: The next step is equal to the previous step, plus the change times delta T. Boom. Right?
Christian Hubicki: So that's what that is. So now we'll do dzarray… DZ array iter plus 1… is equal to…
Christian Hubicki: the previous DZ array, DZ array iter.
Christian Hubicki: Plus… dot dot dot… Z double dot.
Christian Hubicki: Which is… which we determined is this equation, Right here.
Christian Hubicki: Now, I could write this all into the line.
Christian Hubicki: Or I could not do that.
Christian Hubicki: I'm gonna just write… Up above here, I'm gonna define…
Christian Hubicki: DDZ on a different line to make my life a little easier.
Christian Hubicki: It's gonna be equal to minus G, plus…
Christian Hubicki: K divided by M… did I define M? I didn't define my mass, friends. I didn't define my mass.
Christian Hubicki: Oh boy, I'll get right back to it. Did I find it? Times L0…
Christian Hubicki: minus Z of T. See that? It's all right there.
Christian Hubicki: minus Z of T. So whatever our current position is, so it's Z array, Hitter.
Christian Hubicki: This is just a cleaner way we define the acceleration on different lines, so it's all not on one line. That's all I'm doing.
Christian Hubicki: I'm also noticing I did not define, … did I define L0 and K? I defined L0, K, and I never defined M.
Christian Hubicki: So scrolling up, M is 1 kilogram.
Christian Hubicki: Boom.
Christian Hubicki: Great.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? M is now defined as 1.
Christian Hubicki: We have these double, double dot, and now we go back down to Euler's method right here.
Christian Hubicki: So now we're gonna add… Our second derivative, which is… DDZ, times… Delta T.
Christian Hubicki: And… That's the loop!
Christian Hubicki: Some people write the light, write the right, and loop.
Christian Hubicki: Sure.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Alright, now we just need to do some plotting. Let's do some plotting… We're gonna plot.
Christian Hubicki: The height over time.
Christian Hubicki: Okay, so that's going to plot our time array.
Christian Hubicki: And I'm gonna plot our Z array.
Christian Hubicki: And I'm gonna make it a black line, I'm gonna do my line width, as 3.
Christian Hubicki: Alright.
Christian Hubicki: Label my axes…
Christian Hubicki: It's gonna be time in seconds.
Christian Hubicki: And my Y label is gonna be our height in meters.
Christian Hubicki: Alright.
Christian Hubicki: If we did that right, and I run it, that should create a nice little plot for us.
Christian Hubicki: Look at that!
Christian Hubicki: It's springing!
Christian Hubicki: To use a technical term.
Christian Hubicki: But the physicists among you, or the physics-inclined among you, might notice a little, a little…
Christian Hubicki: issue with the simulation. Does anyone want to point out
Christian Hubicki: What might not be quite accurate.
Christian Hubicki: about my model here. What about the simulation?
Christian Hubicki: This is a energetically conservative system.
Christian Hubicki: And yet…
Christian Hubicki: Because it's just, if I go back to my equations here, my system, it's just a spring, no losses, no impacts, it shouldn't be gaining or losing energy. And yet, looking at my…
Christian Hubicki: Plot here, it's gaining energy, it's oscillating, it's going, right?
Christian Hubicki: Why? What, do we screw up?
Christian Hubicki: Well, one thing you gotta remember is that Euler's method is an approximate method.
Christian Hubicki: Right? It's an approximation.
Christian Hubicki: Assuming that you've picked a small enough
Christian Hubicki: The spring has no max length, that's another thing, it will launch into the air without a max length, that's true. That's also true autumn. We will get to that in 15 minutes. Watch.
Christian Hubicki: But even more importantly.
Christian Hubicki: That DT that I chose, I kind of hand-waved, that I chose.01, might not be small enough.
Christian Hubicki: Let's make it .001.
Christian Hubicki: And rerun it.
Christian Hubicki: Much better, right?
Christian Hubicki: Not gaining as much energy.
Christian Hubicki: That's because, if you recall, from Euler's method waaaay the heck back here.
Christian Hubicki: Here's Euler's method. Look at that approximation, right?
Christian Hubicki: Whoa, there it is.
Christian Hubicki: It assumes it's small enough.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: And so, I'm assuming that some of you are asking yourselves, well, how do you know if it's small enough?
Christian Hubicki: Great question!
Christian Hubicki: And there is a whole numerical science to determining that, but there are tools
Christian Hubicki: inside of MATLAB, and most programming languages, that will choose it for you.
Christian Hubicki: Or, even more importantly, it will determine when in the simulation it needs to be smaller than others.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? Like, if this system is not accelerating very much.
Christian Hubicki: Having a long time step's totally fine.
Christian Hubicki: Just like if you were in your car, if you knew you were going exactly 60 kilometers an hour, you're going exactly that speed.
Christian Hubicki: you could say, oh, that means in an hour from now, I'll know I'll be 60 kilometers away, just because I know that super precisely. But if you're speeding up and slowing down a lot, you would have to use smaller and smaller time steps to make that calculation, right?
Christian Hubicki: So… In MATLAB,
Christian Hubicki: There's actually a function for it.
Christian Hubicki: It's called ODE45, and there are many versions of… let me see if I can get this bigger here. I don't know if I can make that bigger.
Christian Hubicki: In the moment, but…
Christian Hubicki: You can say, help ODE45, and it is a method of simulating ordinary differential equations, ODEs.
Christian Hubicki: If you give it the right information. Well, what information is that?
Christian Hubicki: Oh!
Christian Hubicki: It integrates, and if you can read that, a system of differential equations.
Christian Hubicki: Y prime is equal to F of TY.
Christian Hubicki: A system of first-order differential equations. Oh my goodness, isn't that exactly what we were doing?
Christian Hubicki: Yes, it was.
Christian Hubicki: Right?
Christian Hubicki: The way we've been defining… These systems… Look.
Christian Hubicki: Couple of first-order differential equations right there, right?
Christian Hubicki: And ODE45, and it's just one of many methods, That they have.
Christian Hubicki: allows you to then, to simulate more accurately. Let's use it really quickly, okay? Just so you have an example, because it's such an important tool, okay? But the idea is if you can define
Christian Hubicki: Your state vector, remember we talked about it, Y. Oh my goodness, it's almost like we… I didn't make all this up. It's like it's a real thing, right?
Christian Hubicki: You know, it has a bunch of state variables in a list, and we'll call them… they can be anything. They could be, you know, Y1, Y2…
Christian Hubicki: Whatever, is equal to… some function, of time?
Christian Hubicki: and state.
Christian Hubicki: And that's literally what we did for our swing-loaded vertted pendulum here, right?
Christian Hubicki: We rewrote
Christian Hubicki: Sorry.
Christian Hubicki: and… sorry, and it's Y dot of T.
Christian Hubicki: There we go, Y dots, right? We wrote the derivative of our state As being dependent on just
Christian Hubicki: States, and also time.
Christian Hubicki: Okay.
Christian Hubicki: So if we wanted to use ODE45, how do you use that? Let's pull it up.
Christian Hubicki: Let's have ODE45 do the same thing.
Christian Hubicki: What do you need? So ODE45 says it needs a couple of things. It needs an ODE function.
Christian Hubicki: which is those equations that I showed you. We're gonna put them in a new function file, okay? A time span, and an initial condition.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: So what I'm gonna do really quick.
Christian Hubicki: is I'm going to create a new file, New file.
Christian Hubicki: It's gonna be a function file. It's gonna be function.
Christian Hubicki: And it needs to return to… it needs to return…
Christian Hubicki: One thing is called Y, you know, Y prime, or DY.
Christian Hubicki: is equal to ODE, and it takes in the current time and the current state, Y.
Christian Hubicki: So, for instance, for our We'll call it, yeah, we'll call it ODE Fun.
Christian Hubicki: Because it's enjoyable.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Inside the function, we would have to define our mass, our gravity.
Christian Hubicki: There are ways to define it outside and pass it in.
Christian Hubicki: We can talk about that offline if we want, just make sure we have time here. And… is that all we need? L0, G… yeah, I think that's it for inside the loop.
Christian Hubicki: I think that.
Monica Daley (she, her): You don't need K.
Christian Hubicki: K…
Christian Hubicki: Okay, thank you, Monica. Thank you, much appreciated.
Christian Hubicki: Okay, I'm being sloppy in defining this really quickly without comments, alright? But what you need to do is send back the derivatives of your state
Christian Hubicki: Depending upon the… depending upon the current state.
Christian Hubicki: So, thankfully…
Christian Hubicki: We can define our first state here. We're gonna say that
Christian Hubicki: That Z , the derivative of our first state, Z of T, okay?
Christian Hubicki: call it DZ. So our first state is going to be the first element of Y.
Christian Hubicki: So it's Y of Y1, okay?
Christian Hubicki: Because it's the first one there. We just defined it there. DZ is equal to Y2.
Christian Hubicki: This is our position.
Christian Hubicki: We call that the first state in our little list here?
Christian Hubicki: And here we got our second state, velocity.
Christian Hubicki: Second state?
Christian Hubicki: Okay? We defined… we got the states in from Y.
Christian Hubicki: And then our job is to send back DY, the derivative of each of these states. Okay?
Christian Hubicki: So DY… We gotta send back in a vector.
Christian Hubicki: First, the derivative of Z, which we know is DZ. Well, guess what?
Christian Hubicki: We now know DZ.
Christian Hubicki: Done.
Christian Hubicki: This is a derivative.
Christian Hubicki: With respect to time, of each state.
Christian Hubicki: And the derivative of our second state.
Christian Hubicki: Z dot, which is gonna be…
Christian Hubicki: Z double dot, otherwise known as… Minus G?
Christian Hubicki: plus K over M.
Christian Hubicki: times L0.
Christian Hubicki: Minus?
Christian Hubicki: Z.
Christian Hubicki: Done.
Christian Hubicki: And so what ODE45 does, and there's other… what it does is it needs to be given this function.
Christian Hubicki: And that's how it knows what your dynamical system is, okay, for it to simulate, okay, and for it to solve.
Christian Hubicki: So really quickly, I'm going to create a new, …
Christian Hubicki: A new function fi- a new script file.
Christian Hubicki: I'm gonna call it, … Slip, 1D… ODE45.
Christian Hubicki: dot M.
Christian Hubicki: To show you how easy it is to use. Slip, 1D, ODE45, dot M.
Christian Hubicki: Make this really fast.
Christian Hubicki: CLC clear, close all.
Christian Hubicki: Not even commenting well. Shame on me.
Christian Hubicki: And then we're gonna use ODE45,
Christian Hubicki: All we need to define for it is the ODE function, so we're gonna… so it says it's gonna give us a time vector T,
Christian Hubicki: So a time array…
Christian Hubicki: And it's gonna give us… a state… Array.
Christian Hubicki: And ODE45 requires that we give it an ODE function, and the way that we tell it it's a function, we say at
Christian Hubicki: ODE… Fun.
Christian Hubicki: Then you have to give it a time span?
Christian Hubicki: Put that in a little vector.
Christian Hubicki: Actually, I'll define it up above so you can see the time span.
Christian Hubicki: Where do you want it to start? Where do you want it to end?
Christian Hubicki: 0 and 10.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: And also, we need to know our initial conditions, so our initial position, which is our first variable, is 1.
Christian Hubicki: Initial velocity is 0.
Christian Hubicki: Do we give it the time span?
Christian Hubicki: And we give it Y0.
Christian Hubicki: And ODU45 will simulate our system, it'll choose all of its own little delta T's at different points of time that it seems that the Ts are appropriate.
Christian Hubicki: And the states at each of those points in time.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? So I'm gonna run it, and I'm gonna show you what's in these timer… oh, did I screw up?
Christian Hubicki: … what I not define here?
Christian Hubicki: ODE fun…
Christian Hubicki: DY… All in logical energy positive… oh, oh, there's a… I forgot the multiplication there.
Christian Hubicki: See that?
Christian Hubicki: Actually, I have this fancy device.
Christian Hubicki: Work.
Christian Hubicki: So anyway, you can see that multiplication that I missed.
Christian Hubicki: Gotta save it, gotta rerun the code, make sure it works.
Christian Hubicki: And you can see that the time array, if I just hit time array, enter.
Christian Hubicki: You can just see it's a bunch of points in time.
Christian Hubicki: that it shows how fast they should move and not. You see that the increments are not consistent.
Christian Hubicki: It's choosing one to have small time steps, one to have big time steps.
Christian Hubicki: And if you look at the state array.
Christian Hubicki: What is it? It's two columns.
Christian Hubicki: It's gonna be the same number of rows as time steps, so this entire first column is our position, and the entire second column is our velocity.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: So, if we want to plot our position over time, we plot our time array.
Christian Hubicki: And just the first column of our state array.
Christian Hubicki: And in MATLAB, if you want the whole column, you say, hey, I want all the rows, which would be colon, comma 1, which is the first column.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: Then I'm gonna make it there, and I'm gonna make the line width… 3…
Christian Hubicki: Should be able to run that.
Christian Hubicki: And there we go.
Christian Hubicki: It chose the time step, so that way the oscillation doesn't get bigger and bigger and bigger and add more energy, right? It was smart about it. Now, how does it do that?
Christian Hubicki: The way it does it is it actually uses a higher-order integration method, called Runga-Kata.
Christian Hubicki: And there are many versions of it. There's, like, a fourth order, and a fifth order, and fifth order's gonna be better than fourth order, right? And you can keep adding more and more orders that are more and more precise. And what it does is it says, I'm gonna try doing a fourth order step
Christian Hubicki: And a fifth order step.
Christian Hubicki: And see how different they are.
Christian Hubicki: And based on how different they are, that tells me how much smaller I need to make my time step. That's why it's called ODE45. It uses those 4th order and fifth order methods. …
Christian Hubicki: At least that's the simple way I like to explain it to people. So, it's actually not too complicated to code up. So, that's how you can have it choose the time step for you, right?
Christian Hubicki: But… One thing we haven't done is limited
Christian Hubicki: the… we have not limited the length of the spring. I forget who mentioned that. We're gonna make this jump. I promise we'll make a jump, and we have 4 minutes. I think we can do it.
Christian Hubicki: I think we can, friends.
Christian Hubicki: Alright?
Christian Hubicki: And this is where it gets a little bit tricky.
Christian Hubicki: And I'll give you the high-level version, because what we have done is we have defined our dynamics as this one differential equation, right?
Christian Hubicki: That one differential equation defines our dynamics.
Christian Hubicki: But our dynamics are different when our feet are on the ground versus off the ground. We have to switch between whether or not we have a leg on the ground, whether we have a leg on the ground, therefore have a spring force, versus when we don't, okay? And when you have a switch in those dynamics.
Christian Hubicki: It goes from being called what we would call a continuous, Dynamical system.
Christian Hubicki: To what we would call a hybrid.
Christian Hubicki: dynamical system.
Christian Hubicki: Legged locomotion is commonly understood to be a hybriddynamical system. If you talk to hardcore mathematicians about it, they would say, technically, a hybrid dynamical system is when your state jumps instantaneously at some point, and then smoothly moves again. We talked about state. We know what state is. It's the state variables, right? That's what they're talking about.
Christian Hubicki: And colloquially, I'd like to say it's when the dynamics switch.
Christian Hubicki: Well, here we have a pretty easy way of doing this. So the only difference for our little model
Christian Hubicki: Is that when it's in the air.
Christian Hubicki: It's only under the force of gravity.
Christian Hubicki: Not the spring.
Christian Hubicki: So…
Christian Hubicki: What I'm gonna do is have a little if statement that says, if I'm past the spring length, the spring length.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? I'm gonna make the spring cut force zero.
Christian Hubicki: That's all I'm gonna do. Super easy version of this. There are smarter versions, which I will hint at, because I think we can actually do this, in 90 seconds.
Christian Hubicki: So, here, I have… I mean, back in my Slip1D code, and I have this DDZ command.
Christian Hubicki: So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna say… I'm gonna say F, the force in the spring.
Christian Hubicki: It's gonna be equal to all of this, okay? I'm gonna cut this out, cut it, There, and say…
Christian Hubicki: and I'll get rid of the divide by M. The force in the spring is going to be that, F spring, divided by M. You can check the math, that math should work, right? That should be the exact same result if I run it, …
Christian Hubicki: Where it screwed up. Oh, extra parenthesis there.
Christian Hubicki: If I run it, I should get the same result I got before.
Christian Hubicki: Sure enough, I did.
Christian Hubicki: Okay?
Christian Hubicki: So what I'm gonna say is that if… Z… array iter, the current height, iter, is greater than L0,
Christian Hubicki: That means it's off the ground.
Christian Hubicki: That means the force in the spring is zero.
Christian Hubicki: Otherwise… Else…
Christian Hubicki: Otherwise… The force is the force in the spring.
Christian Hubicki: This… Switches… to flight, switches… to stance. We know the flight and stance from…
Christian Hubicki: Alright? So, now if we run this…
Christian Hubicki: Nothing is really any different, because it doesn't really start off the ground.
Christian Hubicki: But if we change the initial condition from being 1 to being, I don't know, 1.5?
Christian Hubicki: And we rerun it.
Christian Hubicki: There we go. It hops, hits the ground.
Christian Hubicki: Hops, hops, hops, it might not look a lot different, but the shape of… when it's in the air versus on the ground is different.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? It's hopping.
Christian Hubicki: Alright?
Christian Hubicki: So, very simply, we change the dynamics into a hybrid dynamic system with an if statement.
Christian Hubicki: This is a little bit sloppy, because
Christian Hubicki: the time step for when it hits the ground, the time step might miss the exact moment where it hits the ground. So it might accrue a little bit of error, this is one way to go, but actually, ODE45 has a beautiful way
Christian Hubicki: Of detecting when an event happens, like hitting the ground.
Christian Hubicki: It's called event detection.
Christian Hubicki: And, I can stick around for a few minutes afterwards to show you how that works, but otherwise, that's… that's how you simulate a system in a nutshell. I mean, how do you get that to running forward? Well, all that changes is that you have… your equations get more…
Christian Hubicki: get more complicated, okay? But the same procedure applies.
Christian Hubicki: you… you take every position and velocity, you put it into your state vector, and you arrange it into that form, except now you would have a forward position and a backward position. You would probably… if you had a… if you had a spring-loaded inverted pendulum that's moving forward like that, where that's…
Christian Hubicki: X, and that's Z.
Christian Hubicki: You would now have a state vector, that has…
Christian Hubicki: X, X dot, Z, and Z dot in it.
Christian Hubicki: And then, in the code, You would have?
Christian Hubicki: Four of these lines, instead of two.
Christian Hubicki: There are nicer ways to write it. I cover it in my Optimal Control class, if you're curious, but thank you for taking me out 90 minutes. I'll pause there. Thank you so much.
Monica Daley (she, her): That was great, thank you.
Christian Hubicki: Thank you.
Christian Hubicki: Hey, any questions or any thoughts, before I go?
Christian Hubicki: Let me show, ….
Autumn Routt: Would you mind explaining why you chose the current value of Z to be greater than L0 as the if statement that switches to flight?
Christian Hubicki: Oh, great question! So why did I choose this condition to be greater than or equal to flight? So I forget, Autumn mentioned, like, hey, we don't have a maximum spring length, I believe, in the chat before, if my memory serves. So…
Christian Hubicki: that, if I go to…
Christian Hubicki: my diagram, okay? The length… the rest length of the spring
Christian Hubicki: When you would… when you are compressing that spring past the rest length, right? That means the spring's in compression, right?
Christian Hubicki: And so, that means the spring is pushing against the ground, the ground's pushing back against the spring, which allows you to spring up.
Christian Hubicki: Now, when the spring lengthens, so when you're past the rest length, when your height's past the rest length.
Christian Hubicki: Right at that instant, your force is zero, right? You're at the rest length of the spring.
Christian Hubicki: Then you go further up.
Christian Hubicki: Okay? Then, if you're still on the ground, that ground's got to tug you back down, right?
Christian Hubicki: But that's not how the ground works. The ground does not suck you to the ground with a suction cup. The ground only pushes force one way, and that's up, right? We call that a unilateral contact, just so we sound fancy. There's contact force in only one way, it's unilateral, right? Which means that it can't suck you back down, that means you're off into the air.
Christian Hubicki: Therefore, you're in flight. So that's why when we pass the rest length.
Christian Hubicki: Because it can't tug us back down, we have to enter it in flight.
Autumn Routt: Okay, yeah, that makes sense. Thank you.
Christian Hubicki: Oh, yeah, it was U.S, yes, exactly.
Autumn Routt: Yeah.
Christian Hubicki: Any other questions?
Christian Hubicki: Just, pop in at any point. I will say, I will not be offended if you have to go, but I'll just point out the thing that, with the ODE event detection, it's very similar to how the ODE45 works, where you create
Christian Hubicki: Instead of a function that…
Christian Hubicki: defines your dynamics. This is your ODE function that we defined. You create an ODE events function.
Christian Hubicki: And it takes in the current time, whatever the current time is, whatever the current state is, and you tell it
Christian Hubicki: How close it is to hitting the event.
Christian Hubicki: And so that's how you can have it detect if it hits the ground or not. And what you will do, typically, is you say, when it hits the event.
Christian Hubicki: Stop the simulation.
Christian Hubicki: And then what you do is you rerun ODE45, you change the dynamics, you change the state, you do all the things that you want to do, like what we did on this math right here.
Christian Hubicki: Alright, like what we did, which is what we turned off
Christian Hubicki: Where we turned off the force.
Christian Hubicki: And on the spring, and then you restart it again. So you keep turning on and off the simulation, that's how it typically works.
Christian Hubicki: Alright.
Christian Hubicki: I really thank you all for following along and your attention. I had a great time, and I enjoyed a lot of the workshops this summer, so thank you all to the prior workshop attendees. Definitely open for next year, simulating something more appropriate to muscle modeling and things like that. I was trying to see if it could fit in a hill type today, but I think we got plenty in today.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah, that was a lot in the time you had. If there are people who are interested in learning more, are your other lectures available online?
Christian Hubicki: I'm gonna put them up on the Slack right after the, right after this. I have a, I have a YouTube playlist.
Christian Hubicki: of my last time I taught Applied Optimal Control. Now, don't be…
Christian Hubicki: if you're not a… if you're like, I don't know what control is, or how to do control, don't be afraid. A lot of it is designed just like this was, assuming that you've never done a simulation before.
Christian Hubicki: So there's a little… so I do tutorials in MATLAB, it's all in MATLAB on how to do simulation, and then optimal control. So I'll post that YouTube playlist for the entire 2025 semester of courses.
Monica Daley (she, her): Great. That would be a good resource. Thank you.
Christian Hubicki: Alright.
Christian Hubicki: Thank you so much, I appreciate everyone.
Monica Daley (she, her): Thanks, everyone.
Monica Daley (she, her): Bye.
Victoria Wood: Bye!